# ZICHEN LIU

## BIOSTATISTICIAN

# CONTACT



hello@zichenliu.me

+1 (408) 480-9624

# **EDUCATION**

## PhD in Biostatistics (in-progress)

University of California, Los Angeles Los Angeles, CA | 2022 -

#### **MS in Biostatistics**

University of Washington Seattle, WA | 2020 - 2022

### **BA in Chemistry**

Pomona College Claremont, CA | 2014 - 2018

# SKILLS

- Data science
- Data visualization
- Statistical modeling
- Simulation studies
- Machine learning
- Artificial neural networks
- Natural language processing
- Agile project management
- High performance computing
- Chem/bioinformatics

# TOOLS

Python, R, Java, SQL, Git, Linux

## PROFILE

I am an incoming biostatistics PhD student at UCLA interested in graduate student researcher opportunities. I have a MS in biostatistics and 3 years of industry experience in both data science and biostatistics research. My work has been featured in 16 publications and 2 national conferences.

## EXPERIENCE

### **BIOSTATISTICS CONSULTANT**

PUBLIC HEALTH — SEATTLE & KING COUNTY | SEATTLE, WA | 2021 - 2022

Designed and executed a statistical analysis plan to model the relationship between 3 types of public housing exits and homelessness using survival analysis and propensity score weighting to adjust for 11 multi-level confounders.

## **GRADUATE INTERN**

GENENTECH | SOUTH SAN FRANCISCO, CA | 2021 - 2021

Independently designed 10+ statistical models to explore associations between respiratory disease health outcomes and physical activity using the UK Biobank database (incl. longitudinal, time-to-event, and high-dimensional biomarker data).

## **BIOSTATISTICS RESEARCH ASSISTANT**

FRED HUTCHINSON CANCER RESEARCH CENTER | SEATTLE, WA | 2021 - 2021

Evaluated the efficiency of novel propensity score weighting methods for the HPTN 096 cluster randomized trial for HIV prevention. Wrote R code to simulate viral suppression in 16 cluster populations and 256 different cluster randomizations.

## DATA SPECIALIST / DATA ANALYST

INSTITUTE FOR HEALTH METRICS AND EVALUATION | SEATTLE, WA | 2018 - 2021

Designed efficient Python pipelines to standardize and load 7 incoming datasets into the clinical database. Improved the disease modeling of 30+ injuries and sexual violence for the Global Burden of Disease Study with spatial-temporal smoothing methods. Using R, created data visualizations of results for 10+ medical journal publications (bit.ly/zichenpubs).